# ALEXANDER NAVARRE

www.github.com/astronavarre/Portfolio

414-213-3236 | aenavarre@gmail.com

Analytical and scientifically-rigorous data scientist with a PhD in astrophysics. Expertise and experience in data handling, modeling, and visualization. Collaborative team player and data storyteller, with experience presenting results to technical and non-technical audiences. Aiming to leverage expert problem-solving and critical thinking skills to extract insights from data, communicate those insights, and use them support business objectives.

# **SKILLS**

- Python
  - Numpy. Scipy, Matplotlib, Pandas, Scikit-Learn, Folium, Seaborn, Plotly, Beautiful Soup, Pygame
- Mathematics & Statistics
  - Statistical Distributions, Evaluation Metrics, Algorithms, Linear Algebra, Calculus, Probability Theory
- Data Handling
  - SQL (specifically mySQL), Tableau Prep, Pandas DataFrames
- Machine Learning
  - Linear Models (GLM, SVM, Random Forests, etc), Unsupervised Models (Gaussian Mixture, K-Means, etc)

- Data Visualization
  - Matplotlib Visualizations, Tableau Dashboards, PowerPoint Presentations
- Misc
  - Microsoft Azure Cloud Computing, Scientific Writing, Linux OS and Command Line Use,
- Physics
  - Classical Mechanics, Electromagnetism, Thermal Physics, Quantum Mechanics, Special Relativity, General Relativity, Astrophysics
- Soft Skills
  - Communication, Curiosity, Storytelling, Adaptability, Critical Thinking, Team Mindset

# **EXPERIENCE**

#### **POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER**

University of Cincinnati | Cincinnati, OH

MAY 2024 - AUG 2024 (CONTRACT)

Postdoctoral Researcher under the astrophysics research group led by Professor Matthew Bayliss. Contributed to the research goals of the SGAS collaboration.

- Developed state-of-the-art Python code to model distorted astronomical objects.
- Performed quality assurance by testing code output across 5 different astronomical fields.
- Discovered and documented critical limitations of the code for data of specific quality.
- Authored the first official usage guide on the above-mentioned software.
- Created install and use guides for multiple research softwares for junior and future group members.

### **GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT**

University of Cincinnati | Cincinnati, OH

OCT 2019 - MAY 2024

Graduate Student Researcher under the astrophysics research group led by Professor Matthew Bayliss. Completed a PhD in physics with a concentration in astrophysics. Presented work at multiple conferences domestic and abroad.

- Conducted extensive Bayesian analysis on Hubble Space Telescope Data to estimate physical properties of galaxies.
- Developed morphological models of bright galaxies to separate their light profiles from fainter objects of interest.
- Wrote over 6000 lines of custom python code to analyze spectra and images, visualizing insights with matplotlib for publications.
- Published a research paper as first author in the Astrophysical Journal.

### **GRADUATE TEACHING ASSISTANT**

University of Cincinnati | Cincinnati, OH

AUG 2018 - JAN 2020

Teaching Assistant for introductory physics lectures, labs, and discussion sections.

- Led discussion sections for 20+ students 3x per week to enhance understanding of class material and promote group problem-solving.
- Conducted laboratory classes for 30+ students on classical mechanics with physical demonstrations to teach proper scientific practices.
- Assisted lecturers by providing one-on-one student support during class.

#### UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign | Champaign, IL

JAN 2015 - MAY 2018

Undergraduate Student Researcher under the astrophysics research groups led by Professors Jeffrey Filippini and Joaquin Vieira. Aided in many smaller research tasks across a variety of subjects.

- Designed and created jigs for building and testing a balloon-borne telescope on the SPIDER 2 project.
- Aided in the physical monitoring of the telescope during cryogenic tests.
- Analyzed 100+ astronomical fields for evidence of newly discovered, gravitationally-lensed quasars.

# **EDUCATION**

# PHD IN PHYSICS SUBFIELD: ASTROPHYSICS

University of Cincinnati

APRIL 2024

**GPA 3.8** 

# BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN PHYSICS MINOR IN ASTRONOMY

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

MAY 2018

**GPA 3.4** 

# **PUBLICATIONS**

### FIRST AUTHOR

Resolving Clumpy vs. Extended Lya In Strongly-Lensed, High-Redshift Lya Emitters

Published in: The Astrophysical Journal

Alexander Navarre et al 2024 ApJ 962 175

### **CO-AUTHOR**

Kim et al. 2022, 2023 Owens et al. 2023 Walker et al. 2023 Sharon et al. 2022

# **CERTIFICATIONS**

### **DATA SCIENCE PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATE**

IBM Data Science via Coursera

**JAN 2024** 

Certificate ID: FL25WXZTQ58N